DUVÁN BALLÉN RODRÍGUEZ SRE & DevOps Engineer

https://www.linkedin.com/in/duva
nballen

duvan.ballen@gmail.com
+57 317 765 0612
Medellín, Colombia

https://duv0-x.github.io

SUMMARY

I have the relentless curiosity of a hacker and the meticulous discipline of an old-school systems administrator. With nearly 18 years of experience working with GNU/Linux servers, networks, automation, and infrastructure, I have recently specialized as a DevOps Engineer and Site Reliability Engineer (SRE).

I work with modern stacks using Kubernetes, Terraform, AWS, and monitoring with tools like X-Ray, NewRelic, Prometheus, Grafana, and CloudWatch. I also have hands-on experience building CI/CD pipelines with Jenkins, CircleCI, and GitHub Actions.

I've managed critical infrastructure (in production) and I'm not afraid of incidents. I'm deeply interested in traceability, observability, and the design of resilient, highly available architectures.

I like to lead teams by example: solving problems through code, logs, monitoring graphs, performance, efficiency, and services availability.

SKILLS

- > AWS Cloud
- > CI/CD

> Github

- > Kubernetes
- > Python
- > Inglés B1

- > Terraform
- > Shell Scripting

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Gekko INS Ltda.

Systems Administrator 2008 - 2010

Administration and maintenance of internet portals, including database management, server maintenance, security, and resource administration using CPANEL.

Siscorp de Colombia SAS.

Developer and Systems Administrator 2010 - 2011

Administration of GNU/Linux servers (Web, Firewall, Proxy, DNS, and Zimbra).

Shell-scripting development on GNU/Linux servers.

Installation, administration, and maintenance of GNU/Linux operating systems on Fedora and CentOS servers.

Installation, administration, and maintenance of the three modules of the PowerFile document management system (Storage, SGD, and BPM) in projects for the Senate and House of Representatives, the Ministry of National Education, the Colombian Federation of Municipalities, the Valle Liquor Industry, among others.

Installation, administration, and maintenance of a Wiki for development documentation.

Installation and administration of a Bug Tracker for reporting software errors.

Document Express.

Developer and Systems Administrator 2011 - 2012

Administration of GNU/Linux servers (Web, Firewall, Proxy, and DNS).

Shell-scripting development on GNU/Linux servers.

Installation, administration, and maintenance of GNU/Linux operating systems on Ubuntu Server, Debian, Fedora, and CentOS servers.

Installation, administration, and maintenance of the three modules of the PowerFile document management system (Storage, SGD, and BPM).

Installation, administration, and maintenance of a Wiki for development documentation.

Installation and administration of a Bug Tracker for reporting software errors.

Shell-scripting development on servers for task automation.

Shortcut Solutions SAS.

Developer and Systems Administrator 2012

Shell scripting development on GNU/Linux servers.

Administration and maintenance of GNU/Linux operating systems on CentOS servers with Parallels Plesk Panel.

Installation, administration, and maintenance of eBD (Development Framework).

Shell scripting development on servers for task automation.

Implementation of a high-availability and high-performance cluster for production web applications.

Ximil Technologies SAS.

Developer and Systems Administrator 2012 - 2013

Shell scripting development on GNU/Linux servers.

Administration and maintenance of ${\it GNU/Linux}$ operating systems on CentOS, Red Hat, and Ubuntu Servers.

Installation, administration, and maintenance of platforms developed by the company.

Shell scripting development on servers for task automation and backups.

PHP5+CSS web development on Joomla CMS for DIMAR portals.

Implementation of email infrastructure using Zimbra for the Colombian National Navy.

Development of installation manuals for platforms developed by the company.

OpenBox Ltda.

Infrastructure Engineer
2013 - 2014

Shell scripting development on GNU/Linux servers.

Administration and maintenance of GNU/Linux operating systems on CentOS, Red Hat, Ubuntu Server, Debian, Endian, PfSense (BSD), and other servers.

Installation, administration, and maintenance of virtualization platforms such as VMware and KVM, security platforms such as pfSense, Endian, IPcop, and SonicWall, email platforms such as Zimbra, Postfix, Amavis, and Dovecot, and telephony platforms such as Elastix, among others.

Shell scripting development on servers for task automation and backups.

Ingenews S.A.S.

Infrastructure Engineer and Development
2014 - 2015

Administration and maintenance of GNU/Linux operating systems on CentOS, Red Hat, Ubuntu Server, Debian, Endian, PfSense (BSD), and other servers.

Shell scripting development on servers for task automation and backups.

Research and development of new, custom technologies.

Zürich de Occidente S.A.

Infrastructure Manager and later Infrastructure Director 2015 - 2018

Administration and maintenance of GNU/Linux operating systems on CentOS, Red Hat, Ubuntu Server, Debian, and other servers.

Administration and maintenance of JBoss, Glassfish, and Payara application servers/clusters on CentOS, Red Hat, Ubuntu, and Debian servers, among others.

Service administration of various services such as Nginx, Apache, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Zimbra, Fortigate, SonicWall, Jenkins, GIT repositories, Docker Hub, and backup systems, among others.

Administration and maintenance of virtualization platforms such as VMware vSphere. Administration and maintenance of services deployed in Azure and Amazon, such as databases, load balancers, and storage services, among others.

Planning and execution of Swarm projects - setup, administration, maintenance, and deployments on Docker Swarm.

Alkanza S.A.S.

DevOps Engineer 2018 - 2019

Setup, administration, and maintenance of Kubernetes clusters.

Cloud infrastructure management on Amazon AWS. Deployment of self-scaling and resilient infrastructure, infrastructure deployment with CloudFormation.

Jenkins administration and setup. Creation of jobs for Kubernetes deployments, database tasks, or creation of jobs for automated software testing.

Lulo Bank S.A.

SRE/DevOps Engineer Mayo 2021 - Present

Design, build, manage, automate, and maintain self-scaling and resilient infrastructure on AWS using services such as EKS, ECS, EC2, S3, SQS, EventBridge, Cognito, DynamoDB, Lambda, API Gateway, Elasticache, among others. All of this is versioned on Github using IaC with Terraform.

 ${\sf CI/CD}$ and infrastructure and microservices deployment automation with ${\sf CircleCI.}$

Observability, traceability, and monitoring using tools such as X-Ray, NewRelic, Prometheus, Grafana, and CloudWatch.

I currently lead a DevOps and SRE team.

EDUCATION

HIGH SCHOOL

• Colegio San Agustín, 2003.

UNIVERSITY

Although I do not hold a university degree, I have completed several semesters at higher education institutions, strengthening my technical and theoretical knowledge—particularly in the areas of systems, electronics, and philosophy:

• **Electronic Engineering** - 6 semesters

Colombian School of Engineering Julio Garavito

• Systems Engineering - 4 semesters

Grancolombiano Polytechnic

• Philosophy - 2 semesters

National Open and Distance University (UNAD)

This academic journey, along with my strong commitment to self-learning, and active participation in open-source communities and research groups, has enriched my professional and technical experience.

ADDITIONAL TRAINING

- Cloud SRE Engineer en AWS
- AWS Solutions Architect Associate (Cloud Architecture Specialist)
- Programming for Everybody (Getting Started with Python)
- <u>Using Python to Access Web Data</u>
- Python Data Structures